I will call the regular meeting, regular meeting of the
Minor City Council for Monday, November 15th, 2021.
Number two, proclamation declaring November,
Native American Heritage Month.
So, the city, the Maryland City Council,
and the President of Proclamation declaring the month of November,
as American, Native Heritage Month,
our Native American Heritage Month, and the city of my own,
encouraging other institutions to recognize the month,
and reaffirming the city's commitment to promote the well-being
and growth of my life as Native American community.
We have several chiefs here today,
and Ottawa County of all counties in the United States,
knows how important our Native American history and heritage is.
We really don't need a month to recognize that here in Ottawa County,
but we felt like something we needed to do,
so we wanted to follow through on that,
what the chiefs, and we're glad you guys could be here tonight.
You're a very integral part of Ottawa County
in the city of my own.
We appreciate the support that you give us as a city,
and this is a council, and there's lots of things in this community
we couldn't do without you, so we appreciate your time tonight.
We thank you for coming, and I would like for all of you to come forward,
so we can present this to you as a council.
All right, all right, all right, all right, all right.
All right, all right.
Thank you, Jay.
Thank you, guys.
Thank you.
Oh, no, I'm blank in here.
Number three, public input and unscheduled personal preferences.
We haven't done tonight.
Four, maximum, consent agenda staff recommends we approve.
Five, through nine.
Do we need to pull out of?
I'm going to pull it on nine, right?
We'll be able to.
To measure it.
So we'll do consent agenda for five, five, five, five, eight.
We'll pull number nine and table that.
We're going to wait about on to be able to do that.
We'll just vote number one.
Do eight.
I'll make a motion.
Second.
Double.
Hi.
E-step.
Davis.
Hi.
So number nine.
I'm not even good.
Make a motion.
We table.
Item number nine and four.
Next counts me.
Second.
E-step.
Double.
Hi.
Davis.
Parker.
10.
Public hearing concerning the ordinance.
Anxing an area adjacent to the city of Miami.
In section seven, township 27 north range 23 east.
On the Indian base in Meridian.
I don't know county Oklahoma into the part of the corporate limits of the city of Miami,
Mr. Ken Wings.
David.
I will take a credit of blame for having this before you tonight.
I had brought to the attention of the city manager and the mayor that called us for
represents dollar general.
The number of matters.
One of them was the development of property hearing from my.
Well, my part is handled that I did not.
The line heard about it.
I just question.
Why are we becoming a part of the city since we're right here.
And we'll be relying on the city for.
Please.
The architecture.
We got to be a part of the city.
So I must.
But to.
You.
We.
The.
proposition for you, the dollar general store owners have consented to the NX.
We believe that we've brought all of our public notices and thank you for the
dollar general.
We've had some conversations with Lee one family who lives the area, but other than that,
I received no other influence.
I'm happy to try to be helpful tonight.
Do we have anyone else from the community that would like to speak on this?
Mr. Darren Shepherd?
I know what I'm fix to say is I'm going to change nothing, but the bottom line is the city
try to do this in the city limits and they've got to turn down my understanding.
So we move out to the county.
I go to the county commission meeting and I'm so like any, they have no buildings.
They have no ordinances.
They have nothing to do with fire protection.
They have zero.
You do what you want.
So the city knew that this business was given to town and we're going to wait till
it's done and completed and then we want to try to annex the NX for tax dollars.
I disagree with it.
The city knew that it was going to happen.
We should have done it then.
So the city could have controlled and done inspections and you know,
where everything along the way to make sure it was done correct.
That's my concern.
It seems like if you're going to come out of them, you're not going to.
They try to build it over time in life.
Spring.
So the legal law.
It's moved back.
Because there is no county ordinances.
So nobody has the respect of the building or what we know.
Or how it was done.
And that's where my concern lies.
And I disagree with all the strength of that simple fact.
The city should have been more involved in it from the work you give you.
They knew.
They responded to you tell them you're still it.
Ordered electric, so they knew what was going to happen.
That's what I'd like to say about it.
Anyone else?
Just me.
If you would, if you would.
If you would.
I'd like to tell the people.
They can help.
No, that's a different one.
That one's not being annexed by the city.
That's what that was.
No man.
This is the one out by Southern Hills Baptist church, South Of town.
That's the one that's the public here.
because I had heard it was out by charging that grocery that it was more than any of you.
No. Not yet.
Chief has had ever been the fire department ever looked at that out there and not tell
it's NXT and so once it's in NXT and we will go out and do inspection and what?
So Chief, could you just, I have to throw you on the spot here, could you give us a brief explanation
of what you're looking for when you go do these inspections?
Do you do live safety inspections?
Do you need to check?
Make sure to have their extinguisher in the panther exits and all the ball.
Outlet's not covered.
We go back and set around the building for our protection.
Just do an annual live safety inspection that looks like life safety issues.
And so Chief, if they were to fail any part of this inspection, what would be the recourse?
They would get a letter and they'd have 30 days to either apply or have a plan.
One hour can make their corrections and those are correct.
And not only that will they have, they'll have to meet Cindy standards too, correct?
I mean, the city will actually go out and inspect the property also, correct?
City codes.
So the building is the way it is right now.
What's there in the city?
We're going to send someone out and inspect it and make sure it's all at the code.
It's not.
They get the letter to get it all up to the code.
Okay.
And that's what you was worried about?
Learn.
Does that help?
I think he's talking more about hearing the building process.
If the city's been more involved during the building process, when it's all going along,
knowing it was going to happen.
The city's been more involved in the building process of this business.
I'm not against the business coming down, guys.
I promise you.
I'm all for that.
I have nothing against that.
But don't go around behind the rules and try to come out of this and exit in.
I don't like that.
Any other comments?
You get to go.
I don't like that.
Any other comments?
You know who speaking?
You're getting?
Any other comments?
All right, then we'll go to number 11 next on its 2021-25 annexing an area adjacent to the city of Mayana
Oklahoma section 7 township 27 north range 23 east of Indian Basin, Meridian on the Cali Oklahoma into as a part of the corporate
Limits of the city of Mayana
It was a map of the area up here
You still have that David
Any questions or concerns from the council members?
I'll make a motion to approve. I'll second
Parker Davis
Uncle
12 resolution cc 2020 21 dash 15
Approving departure from
Limitation of approved this week your 2021-22 budget regarding full-time equivalents
That's pertain to library customer service court and finance
During the budget season you the council approve the resolution that states how many FTEs we have
What makes up FTE is our our time number. It was three at the time. It was a pretty originally
We have 19 full-time people
I'm sorry into we are part time we have 22 and the recognized as an FTE we divide it by three so every three part
14 people people equals one full-time so we had a number of 92 full-time and 7.33 each our time which gave us
If you round they don't actually
59 or 50 useful time equivalents. Back in, there's no doubt here, in October, you agreed to bring over two county dispatchers.
And the county has been to pay for them, so we increase the council increase the FTEs to 194, which gave us 201 full time equivalents.
What we're asking is to change the full time equivalents to 202, and that breaks down into 190s full time.
The full number is four less part time, which gives us six more total of 202.
So the two breaks down into the library with three full time positions. They gain one full time library assistant.
And the estimated annual savings would be 8,069,72.
In customer service and finance, several years ago, we created a position call, it was half customer service representative and half court administrative assistant.
And that was to have a succession plan for a court, because we only have one full time person in there, we have a part time person.
So, you get people that are best, that are invested in what the city does, it's a full time people.
Part time don't have as much, they can come and go as they please, they're less, they're more likely to leave.
So we combined this part time position with a CSR and gave customer service a part time.
It really didn't work well for customer service.
So this is a time because we're having the term not turned over, we had someone leave and we're having some other tire and finance.
So we took a look at all of those positions and we came up with that we could move this administrative part to finance and combined it with one of our accounting clerks positions.
So customer service would lose that part time person they have, we would switch the person that was half a half to a full time customer service.
We would move the court duties to an accounting court position.
And the net loss is losing a part time person and annual savings of $4,013.
That's what we're asking you to do, that is a resolution to do that because we keep that number.
You know, just to boil it down, we have set out and studied our organizational structure.
We've studied the duties and responsibility.
Try to find areas in which we had more need than we had resources.
And try to find a way in the most efficient manner, the most effective manner in the most physically responsible manner to achieve those outcomes.
And this was one of our outcomes was to be able to reduce the number of part time.
positions flipping a couple of those to full-time positions, which gave us the additional
resources to achieve what we wanted to, and it ultimately resulting in a savings overall
budget.
So I think it was a very positive outcome and this is something that's going to create some
efficiency force.
It's a very key area, obviously.
So, I remember having this conversation maybe two months ago when we were in budget
talks and we talked about this number and what we discussed was at that time, we discussed
what we needed to raise this number so that there's not a need to come back and ask
for one more position and now here we are.
We're asking for, I'm not saying that's a good or bad, what I'm concerned is do we need
to raise this to the 202 or do we need to give it a buffer to prevent, what are your thoughts
there?
I understand my thoughts.
Absolutely.
Yeah, and that was really to ask at the time during the budget cycle was did we need to add enough
buffer there so that we could make organizational structural changes during the year without
having to come back and ask for a resolution at the time we didn't have all any, you know,
any of these plans necessary in place that we were presenting at the time and they're kind of evolving
as we go.
If we had a buffer, we could take advantage of it and then report to the council but the way that
we're set up right now because that number is a hard number as these things come up, we can
come present them.
Whatever the council is more comfortable with, it's really not an issue.
We have a very astute council that is willing to take the time to listen and understand
these type of needs so I would tell you it's not a significant problem for us but welcome to
entertain either way that you can go.
So the only reason I bring up what I brought up was because there's obviously time, energy and effort
putting in to this to come and ask for one person, right?
So resources that it took, I don't know, was it a day, two days, whatever that is, that
was time taken away from doing something else to come and ask for one body.
So if we continue to be, if we think about being good stewards to our citizens and looking at
this kind of, I'll call it busy work for lack of a better term, I know it's important and it's
great that we're saving the money but I just want to, I just want everybody to think through
that to think about, do we want to have a jail or whoever it is to put this together, spend
that time just to ask for one person or do we think about giving a three person buffer so
that there's a little wiggle room.
That's, that's all I have.
And I thought we did discuss that a little bit at one of our council meetings about maybe raising
it a little more than one if need be, right?
We did during the budget cycle.
We did discuss that, but ultimately it was decided we would leave it to where it was but
certainly welcome the discussion and would appreciate the flexibility knowing that they're
still a cap and the budget is still the budget.
You all know one can modify or increase the.
budget other than you all. So as long as we're operating within the budget, that was approved by the council, then the risk is minimal, but we always want to be sensitive to our overall head count because one of our largest expenditures as any entity is is your personnel cost.
So we do remain very sensitive to our overall personnel cost and there will always be a great deal of thought that goes into that before we
modify that anyway, especially increase. It's always harder to decrease than it is to increase. So we're sensitive to that, but the flexibility is certainly welcomed and would give us the ability to continue looking for future changes because there will be future modifications. I don't know if those will be increases or decreases.
Especially with the new dispatch system coming in. We don't know what that's going to.
So you got another mod? I mean 205 is what I'm thinking of instead of 202 that gives you four additional.
So what? Can we modify it with the.
Yes, no way. The way we're writing it.
So I make a motion. We approve for 205.
I'll check it.
Hi.
David Parker.
Thank you.
Thank you, Jill.
13 request add Juneteenth and indigenous people's days to the city of Miami holiday schedule.
I think it's no brighter.
I'm not sure if you agree.
Hi. I appreciate the support and I completely agree with you.
Cindy can explain it to you, but in a nutshell, this aligns us with federal holidays and aligns us better with local holidays.
That we do business with here in Miami.
The banks, specifically the Federal Reserve County and others.
And that was really our tip was to align.
And most importantly, wanting to celebrate indigenous people's day.
Absolutely.
Again, all the places in the world that we should be celebrating this is right here in Miami, Oklahoma.
We've been talking about doing greater things to celebrate that holiday in the future.
Some of those may be activities during the day that we want city employees to be able to participate in, such as parades or other activities.
And being recognized as a holiday and aligning with businesses being closed, which I say that it wouldn't be an issue because other businesses are closed as well.
We would be able to participate in those activities and look forward to trying to find greater better ways to celebrate that holiday in particular with all of our tribes locally.
I think is a really exciting opportunity for us here in Miami.
I'll second it.
And working for a tribe, I definitely like that day myself.
I'm not voting no, because I'll see how mean it is to be like that.
Parker.
Hi.
Michael.
David.
Hi.
Thanks, Eddie.
Thanks.
The tourism update.
And tourism summit highlights from Amanda Davis.
In advance, I did hand you guys out of packet that you have a presentation.
If you think going on this weekend, so I didn't write it to get it right in on my event.
We're here tonight.
All right.
So I'm going to do some walk you guys through a little bit of our departments.
And kind of talk about a current, every few for tourism kind of where we're at, where we're going and
include some points for the tourism summit that just happened.
So visit Miami or the CVV.
We're a division of the part into tourism within the city of Miami.
The CVV works to promote Miami and Northeast Oklahoma as a tourist destination.
As a tourist destination, while encouraging the overnight stay and adding to the local tax phase, they're increased visitor spending.
We like to say that we turned dollars.
One of the things in tourism, we deliver cash to communities.
It's an immediate return in the best month.
Folks are coming in.
They're spending new dollars.
And I'm not really only here in Miami, but it's something that we are very passionate about throughout the entire county.
You know, our team, we say that we've got to be relentless.
We've always got to be on the go.
Because it's important for us to educate the community that, you know, having a healthy and vibrant city in county.
It's very important to continue to grow this industry.
The visitor is always our focus.
It's the core at every decision that we make and everything that we do is about visitors spending.
All right.
So this is a slide that I'm really excited about.
I know I've shared this in different meetings before, but when we talk about tourism and rural Oklahoma,
we talk about Ottawa County as a whole.
So this is a report that was done through the Oklahoma Department of Tourism.
They do it every year.
It's through Dean Rinyans Associates.
If you're familiar with statistics and reports and everybody that studies,
who we are, this is a pretty powerful story for what happens in Ottawa County.
So you guys can see they're the breakdown.
They're along the bottom.
So Ottawa County in our region.
We did $330 million of visitor spending in the year 2019.
And that is a slew of, it's not just what the CBB does.
It's a huge part of what our tribal partners.
I mean, seeing them here tonight with Los Angeles, some of them have stayed.
And they are so important for what we do and who we are.
And when you talk about $330 million,
those dollars continue to turn over in your community.
They're providing jobs and they're adding to the quality of life,
which is what tourism does.
Something that's important to know about this.
and I didn't put it in the notes, but if you take Ottawa County and you take Delaware County
and add those two numbers together, we are the third largest area for visitors spending in the
entire state of Oklahoma behind Tulsa, and that's something for all of us. I mean, we have,
I talk about a tourism team, a lot of people say Amanda, it's not Amanda, it's a team, it's our
tribe, it's our county, it's our city folks, a lot of things that we do from, you know what, people are
here at City Hall that pay bills for us, people are here that, you know, we do events, they jump in and say
how can we help you? So it's such a team effort, and that's just, that's a number that when we look at
as a staff, we're pretty darn proud of that number, because there's a lot of people that contribute to that.
So another important thing, along with that, and it's, I included some stuff in your packet, if anybody
really audience, I'm more than happy to give them a packet as well. But right now, I know in DRA, we talked earlier
and Danny had some numbers from the Arts Council, so this study that just came out a couple of weeks ago,
we used to talk about the daily spend in Oklahoma, it's about $74 a say, when somebody comes in
stays in Miami, whether it's, you know, with one of our tribal partners, whether it's in a property,
a hotel property that's in city limits, we would say on average, they spend about $74 a day, that number now,
from statistics as a hundred and six dollars a day. So you think about everybody that comes in,
they're contributing to that $330 million each dollar, so every new dollar, all of us are levels that are in the
sharing most of us. So we support the economy in different ways. The idea about really growing your economy and how do you do that?
How do you find new streams of revenue in Oklahoma? Being a Nepalese live and buy by sales tax? We just do,
it's what funds are basic services, so how do we get more of that money? So police and fire and parks and
library and all of the different departments, tourism, falls in that as well. How do we buy the way to have more dollars that come in?
We have to continue to see new streams of revenue. So I just want to give you guys a few highlights,
it's a lot of tax, so I promise it's not going to be, I'm just going to hit a few things.
These are some of the things that we have in place, this is who we are, and some of the active campaigns that we have on our
visit my in the team right now. So you guys will remember a few years back, we participated in a new program,
that the state was doing through this image and we have our new art own visit. My I'm a okay app,
if you haven't downloaded it, you need to download it. Right now we currently have 4,180 users,
right, this is now through from January to October. So we've had 17,945 page views. This is just
statistic in marketing for us, this big volumes, because a lot of people you hear him talk about balance rates,
we have a very very low balance rate. So if you guys are online and you click on something and I
know I didn't really want that and you jump off of it really fast, that hurts our balance rate. Like if
a marketer they're like they want you to stay on their website. So the fact that people are staying on our app for two minutes and 43 seconds
is a really really, really.
get transferred as 60% new users this year, 40% returning users. You can see some of the
top locations there, and a lot of this is centered around some of the different marketing
things that we have, some of our target markets right now. One of them, and you'll look at it
and you'll think, what is Ashburn, Virginia? Why is that in your top location? So Ashburn,
Virginia is one of our top motor coach companies that we work with all the time. They are kind
of a charter company that they send out root 66 trips all across the United States. So that tells
us that they are telling the tour operators to download our app. When you open the app, the very
first thing that comes up is events. I've studied it on going on your 16. Events is what drives revenue
in this city, in this county. We have events, revenues go up. So that's above this for us. And when you
look at that app, and that's why people see me and they're like, I know I have events, I have a gut
to the data. We don't count everybody for fun. We do it because the more that we can push into that
app, and we can push into campaigns, it gets on people's radars. Our website is our next big tool that
we use in tourism. So so far through, this is through the end of October. We have 35,985 hits to our
website. So some statistics here that's really important for us to, for you guys to hit. And if you're
taking notes, you want to take notes on this. So the state, our average demographic, the person that
we are trying to target to say come visit my Emma Oklahoma, and it's been money, is the 55 to 75 year old
retiree, they got discretionary funds, they're traveling, life is good, and they're the folks that
in Danny can attest to this. They're in and out of the Coleman constantly. We see them. We've seen a shift
for about the last really six to eight minutes. Our demographic is starting to shift more to,
it's always been driven by females. The industry will tell you about 71 percent of all
travel decisions are made by females. We don't apologize for that, right? Well, I wish everybody
wanted to take your head and say, yeah, that's right. So here's the interesting thing now. So that
dynamic for my Emma Oklahoma, and you guys can see that. Melusers is 50.7% or a website right now,
females 49.3%. So our demographic right now, we have seen a huge shift in a 24 to 35 year old
male demographic that is going to our website. That's because they're wise for telling them to.
Yeah, maybe not. They're still going to be on. But it's just something to take note of. It's something
that as we continue to plan and as we continue to look at economic development and visitor development,
and we look at where we want to be or who we want to be in five years or ten years, there's a shift
happening there. I don't know if it's other states or other communities in the state are seeing it yet,
but we're seeing that in my Emma. We're seeing a shift to a younger demographic and a male demographic
versus a female demographic.
On our website this year, we've had an 89.62% increase in traffic to our website.
One of the things that we took out of the tourism summit, nine out of 10 Americans will
travel over the next six months, 91% of Americans will travel over the next six months.
And we're seeing that in our numbers, people are searching and looking for things.
Right now, we have 91.2% new users to our website, which is huge.
The other thing you can see there, we've got 10 different states that we're targeting with
shows.
A lot of the shows we go to, we send brochures with the state, just because of the budget
capacity.
Sherry and I, a lot of times, will take turns going to those different travel shows.
We go, we set up, we're passing out visitor guides, she'd appreciate me if she knew I
shared her a picture of it, that's her at the show in St. Louis last year, it's a women's show.
And we'll go through probably about 8 to 9,000 guides at these 10 different states.
One of the things I'll say to you is if you guys have followed with what outdoor stuff is
doing, Grand Lake is hot right now, their numbers were, our numbers are crazy, high right
now, Grand Lakes numbers were off the charts, state parks numbers, Matt Pennell told us last
week, they were up 2 million visitors to the Oklahoma State Parks last year, then what they
had done before.
So the outdoor, catching on things like that, anything that we can do to try to get this folks
that's going to the lake to stop your first, drop some dollars here before they go, that's
going to continue to be part of what we work on.
So the next one, you can see some of our assets that we've got in place right now, we've had a
very aggressive campaign using the Coleman Neon sign, really tooting where it's 66, kind of on
the hotels and what the states doing.
It's been a very, very successful forest so far, a lot of people that Sherry works with, that
we're sending stuff out to constantly, we'll say, hey, we love the postcard that has a neon
cone sign so we're like, okay, it's getting people are seeing it.
The one next to it, that's an ad set that we ran in USA today, they do a sign of travel guide.
So we did that just really trying to push people to our website and then you can see our visitor
guide and that's supported pretty much all of our tribal nations, all support our guide and
do ads for the casinos, hotels do that, we have restaurants that do that and convenient stores.
We have over the last two years, we used to do 150,000 guides, we've went down to 90, but
it's only because more people are going and getting things online, so we've just had to
shift a little bit with that one.
So the last thing on this page and on it and we'll move on, so these are, you can go to travel
okay.com in any time and request a brochure, any brochure in the state if you're going somewhere.
Well, we have the Miami brochure on there, so if you go click on it, they mail it to you, they
send me the bill for the shipping, really, really cool deal.
So last month, keep in mind, we just talked about that shift in demographics.
So California is normally in our top 10, so in October of 2021, they just went to our
number two states, I've requested, if we're going to make it.
about my mobile home. So our demographic is shifted.
More people are working from home. And now we have California requesting
my mobile home information. So I think we're on to something there as we
continue again to move forward to think about where we're going. There's a new
demographic. I think that we've got to be aware of. Another thing that Bill
guys shares with us, 76% of Americans, Bill, it's crucial to be outdoors. So I
know that Kevin and Justin and their team with what they're doing with the
Tribal Project. We're going to have to know about the splash pad. That's
huge for us. That's just a domino. I think they'll continue to go and go. So
this next one at the top to kind of show you where we're at and where we're
removing. That graph is all we're really going to focus on. So that is our hotel
tax collection right now. And if you look at the blue, the blue was 1920. You can kind of see
as we got there to the end. Number one is July because we are on a disco here with
the city's budget. So you can kind of see what happened along the blue. Then you
can obviously see what happened with orange. You can kind of see where blue and orange
started fall off there at 567. Those were really, really tough COVID months that
was hard on everybody. But then you'll see as we moved out of February into March. If
you look at 9 and 10 where the orange is, spoon bill season hit, fishing season at
Grand Lake hit, events are tribes started doing just a fantastic job of getting
events back into venues. We had all this stuff happening and look at what it's done to
our collections. We've had seven months of record collections. We're at 80% right now in
hotel tax collections in the city of Miami. So that's just an important thing that we
look at it and a Jill tracks it with this as well. We watch those numbers very closely to
make sure that we know how that's trending. The other thing you guys can read that
on your own, it just gives you an idea that's about 17 active marketing campaigns that
we have going on right now promoting travel to the Northeast Oklahoma into the city. So the
next slide is kind of wrapping it up. This is something that we learned from Bill Guy's
this, the tourism summit. You know, everything begins with a visit. Tourism. He likes to tell you
is the first date to economic development. You can see this chart here which is very interesting.
Everything that happens in the business world everything starts with a visit. He tells
you that you've been able to place where people want to visit then you have a place for people
want to live. Once you build a place where people want to live then you have a place where people
want to work. Once you build a place where people want to work then you have a place where they want
to do business. And then once you do that then you're coming back to creating a place again that
people want to visit. So it's a cycle. We've learned this in the tourism industry of the importance
of continuing to work to build those dollars.
So this is one of the things, I would say anybody that's in the audience and I know some
of you guys shared that day with this during the tours on the summit.
This was probably my biggest takeaway.
I was really talking about it.
shared community value.
Bill told us the story about there was a community.
I want to say it was in Wisconsin.
And the city, kind of what,
Jocelyn went through with their Convention Center
about seven, eight years ago.
The city just did not want to continue to put money
into the Convention Center.
They just didn't see the return on investment.
So they started having some real healthy conversations
about where we're going to go with this.
So they had a city council meeting,
they held a public forum, they invited people
to come in, the hotel showed up, the restaurant showed up,
convenience stores, everybody that's impacted
by the non-local dollar show-out.
So they get all the way through it,
and Bill's tell us a story, and he says,
you know, they got to the very last speaker
and have a little lady that owns a flower shop in town.
And she comes walking up to the mic
and very, very well known, respected, and he said,
you know, they're all looking at it like, why are you here?
Like, you, this Convention Center doesn't have anything
to do with you being a florist.
And she said, you guys don't understand
that they're meeting business.
I do all the floral arrangements
for every table at all their bankwits.
I do all the floral arrangements for all their breakout rooms.
I do all the floral arrangements for the welcome bags.
They put in the hotels for all their speakers.
If we don't have this Convention Center, I go out of business.
Because our local tax base cannot support me, great people,
but there's just nothing that's money there doesn't support me.
So that was really, there's so many things
that tourism can impact, you know,
the $330 million of visitor spending is massive for our county.
It's massive.
You know, not everything's going to translate over into tax dollars.
We wish it did.
But the idea is that all that money coming in
is creating jobs, providing quality of life.
And it's doing what we talked about earlier.
If there's more dollars coming into the city,
it's more dollars per place in fire.
Your goal is that that's more dollars for other things coming in.
It starts small, but over a long time,
our goal and our hope is that it would continue to build.
Another thing you talked about that day is,
and it's hard to track, but a lot of times we say visitors come in.
If we can't see, you know, the immediate return on what they're doing.
When our hotels are full, you know what?
They're all using electric.
They're all using water.
They're using things that find their way back to the city.
So that's an important thing as well.
And then this is the last thing, and I'm not going to go through all of it.
It's something else you guys can read.
We talked about some of it.
Leisure travel right now or is our future.
I mean, we've really got to capitalize.
We're right on Route 66.
We're right on Highway 69.
We're right on Interstate 44.
I know there's a lot of opportunity.
There's things in the works.
We just have to continue to think about the things.
We do how that sets us up for the future.
I know when we had the Heritage Fest,
we have some sponsors that was in for that event.
And I've had some of them call me.
I know some of you guys have had some of them call you.
Some of them have business partners that have come back and then sight visits.
For possible new businesses here in our community that wouldn't have happened if we didn't have the right people.
at that event. So sometimes we don't think about that triple down effect that things like that can happen.
One of the things Bill shared and we talked a little bit earlier was outdoor space of the must.
So as we start thinking forward as a city and we start thinking about how are we going to continue to be competitive?
How do we want people to choose us? We're competing against Tulsa, we're competing against Springfield.
All these places on 66, we have to find a way to think outside of the box. We really did as we went forward.
Connect and communicate and that was the big thing with the tourism summit.
We had a situation about a year ago kind of coming out of COVID. Once we got the green light from the state, we went full blast about nine, ten straight weekends of softball and baseball tournaments.
Because we knew that this economy needed that. They needed the money coming in.
So we had a convenience for a call us on a Monday. It was a weekend that I think Fairline Athletics had softball going on.
We had a big baseball tournament going on. Anyhow had a tournament going on.
And they call us on Monday and you know we constantly are trying to get these people connected with the city and emailing stuff out to them.
And they said you have got to let us know when the stuff's going on. We ran out of every single thing we had and stopped to make pizza and sandwiches.
Like it killed us and if we would have known we could have triple our order and we could have maintained it.
And I said we've been here multiple times. We just need an email address. If you'll just give us an email address, you'll be on every single thing that we send out.
So that's something we've got to continue and we'll share that in the summit. We've got to continue to communicate.
And then the last thing on there and I shared it earlier, hotel tax right now.
We are a little over a half a million dollars up in the first quarter, which is just crazy.
I tried to quiz some people. We had tourism folks from across the state.
Pretty much every CDB director in the state of Oklahoma was here last week if that tourism summit.
I couldn't get a lot of them. Some of them talked about it. Nobody was in the 80% range.
So I, you know, as we move forward, we'll continue to see what other communities are doing.
And then Mike sent out the sales tax report today as well. That was huge.
We're up to 10.18% right now in this fiscal year, which is amazing for our community.
And then the last thing is just our team.
So I'm very fortunate to work with some great, great folks, not just at the CDB, but everywhere across the city.
And we're just fortunate to be able to do what we get to do.
And if you didn't get to come to the summit, I know everybody was working, but it really was a great day.
It's good.
The questions are.
Well, I want to say thank you.
I've been to a lot of the events you put on, and that you brought it for the city.
You do a great job.
You're a great teammate whenever I'm working with you stuff because you're a go-getter.
You go get it done.
And you don't let anything stop you. You don't even stand your way.
And you just, you focus and you get it done.
And we appreciate that the the festival we got through on your light and you entertain next to you that great
We go it went into that same we know where things don't go wrong. We know we don't learn from
We really didn't have anything goes wrong things go wrong
And that was because your leadership on that so I greatly appreciate that because it was an unknown
We didn't know how it was gonna work out. We didn't know there'd be 10 people or you know how many people's gonna be there
Worked out great and like you said the impact has been really great
Economic development wise because I know bone I both have got calls from like she said perspective businesses that want to come here
That it have came here and looked and talked to us and things are still moving forward with those things and they're good
They're positive and they look like they're probably gonna happen
So it's great things like she said just from getting people in your community to let them see it
Otherwise those people may have never been here before so I
I
I've made a statement on the news
I'll go play interviews and it says a couple of times that I want my local home look to be the entertainment capital the force they'd area
Not a mean it and I call chief Harper because I know we're gonna need his help
And he said his response was this is gonna be fun
So we we've got great partners that are willing to step up with us and take this on because we all know how important it is and we got people like this driving the ship
It's easy to get on board
And so and Danny's gonna be up here in a minute and he's gonna be a part of the same conversation
They'll make us their entertainment capital the force that area we can do this and this is looking drive this economy here and the number she quoted
They're not fake. They're not overbone. They're real and those we got a capture every bit of that thought those dollars we can because
We get calls about roads
We get calls about parks we get calls about a lot of different things that we don't have the money to fix and we don't have
The money to put in here's where we get to money the money's there
We just got to go get it. We got to get people get here and spend it and I promise you if they spend it here
Then we can do those things for people but until we get them here. It's gonna be tough
So I asked that everybody get behind her team if you ever wanted to volunteer we can use it
I know Danny really used you to so but we've got to do this as a team as a community
And I know our tribal partners are ready to get it
So that's the community. I know that's the council we're ready. So that's an exciting time and
I look forward to what we get done and Saturday was great
It was a lot of fun. It would brought back old memories from the old days of how it used to be and maybe next year
We can even be bigger because of Lawrence working on it already our girls to have enough fingers downstairs and upstairs and have both
The bank who were in the gymnasium floor. Absolutely. I may have mentioned
to before because I'm obsessed with softball and use athletics in my own, but what happens
when you raise three daughters, right? But a man is team and I don't know who did it and
if I've said it before I apologize now. Hera and Maldro spent motel nights here as softball
teams, playing in the regional that we had out here in October. And I heard through the great
vine that coaches were coming to administration at the high school because their rooms had been
loaded with welcome kits from this office. Promoting not sales tax or not any of that stuff
just saying welcome to my Emma. Little things matter, they left here, all I did was announce
and walk around asking people if they were having a good time and being treated well. That's
all I did for two days. And they just put it on and on and on about the way they were treated
in my Emma. That is how the effort of this team, these department heads, and that's how we
fix and motivate a culture shift. So it little stuff matters, it's all I want to say about
loading a motel around to coaches notice and sometimes coaches don't notice anything but
that meant something to them. I'll add on to that at the festival we have the acts here, Jared
Diva and Thompson Square, they came to us and told us they had never been treated any better anywhere else.
That's a big statement going from those people because they played a different town almost every night
but they said they'd never been treated any better than here. And usually even the band members came
to us and said that because usually the star gets all the attention, the band members felt like they
got just as much attention and really appreciated the fact that they were taken care of and you know people
were asking if they needed anything and so they were all eager to come back. And so one of these days
we might be able to have them come back but that means something if people go and tell other people
how they were treated here and especially if it's positive because they're going to tell people
they're treated negative too. So it's big. She makes hard job easy. A lot of good people go in
in the same direction. And the other question is for a man. Thank you Amanda. Appreciate it. Tell your team
thank you as well. The 15 update on current and future events at the Columbia Theatre, Mr. Dana
Dylan. I'm Marcia Dawson.
I'm going to start out kind of like Amanda did just talking about the mission.
The common theater is dedicated to providing quality arts and educational programming,
that foster appreciation and community pride,
all maintaining and promoting the historic significance of the theater.
And the theater is also the first down at the 266 Cultural District,
whose mission includes the goal of creating a more vital and animated downtown
and increasing economic activity by supporting arts and cultural venues and events
that will attract residents and visitors to the district.
So on that same team and one of the on that same team,
I'm going to have Danny talk a little bit about events.
And I will tell you that he has a whole type list.
And I've been up all I have at the time,
but I'm going to let you go ahead and talk about those.
And then I'm going to talk a little bit about the why not on the event after that.
This page, we were talking about things that go on around the moment.
I look back at last year's calendar.
Now, as you look through these, if you look through these months,
I just took a month at a time, looked down to calendar,
and saw what we had on the calendar for that day.
Starting in July of 20.
And so just so you can see with the variety of things.
There's really a lot of fun working at the theater on a daily basis.
Because you never ever know what's going to happen.
And I said, it's a whole lot of fun.
I was teaching school.
It's kind of like you're doing one thing for about an hour.
And then about rings and you change it and go in another direction.
And that happens throughout our days at the Coleman.
So as you look through there, you can see that it is a range of things.
Not just concerts and not just huge big concerts,
but those are there.
But the ballrooms being used for recessions,
the ballroom book launch, the just tours of different groups that come through.
Sometimes do a lunch on stage and the tour,
or they might do a dinner in the ballroom and a movie.
And so we have a lot of things that go on.
And these groups come in, Amanda.
If they send that groups, they bring us groups.
We have people that contact us all of the time from all over.
And come in and they are always very complimentary of the town of the facility.
And there are experienced epic Coleman.
I don't think there's really a reason to read it.
every one of these things, but you can see yourself
that there's just a wide variety of things that happen
throughout the year at the Coleman.
And as I also said, some of these have been
still not happened in your 21 to COVID
that these were things that were on this schedule.
And some that had been canceled were a race schedule.
We had a huge October when we looked back at that calendar.
I should have put it on here, but I'm not sure.
So we had very many days that we didn't have
a bit of the Coleman, and sometimes we had two or three.
We do that.
We just like to jump up and keep everything going.
We have had a policy that we started during COVID
and that we have maintained.
You can maybe see through that on your work
says, there are two scheduled tours.
We started asking people to schedule their tours if they could.
Give us a call or online, and let us discuss with them
their preference whether they would like to keep their group
separated from other groups.
So it gives them that privilege in case they have been
certain as they travel with them.
They're quite a mix of the people that they don't know
or whatever and keeping their COVID safety.
So we allow for that.
We allow them to make that choice when they call us.
Sometimes I'll say it's fine, whoever wants to join.
Welcome to the joint.
Sometimes I'll say, no, we've prepared a key to our group.
So we honor those requests.
But through that, we have signs on our door that when people arrive,
we let them know that we are here.
We are open, give a knock on the door.
If you don't get any answer quickly, just give us a call.
We're here.
We allow folks to come in any time throughout the day.
Now they may have to wait a little bit of someone's on a tour.
And they didn't want other people joining with them.
Then we might tell them that maybe 15 minutes before your tour begins.
But we kind of find that that operates that way a lot of venues
that you visit across the country's tours or on a schedule of time.
We try to, because of the unique time schedule of people traveling
in 66, we've always tried to accommodate them as they walk in the door.
And it's kind of our goal to not make anybody wait more
than 15 or 20 minutes before we can get them free.
But it's really, we've really had a good year up to this point,
starting with the July season.
Our donations from Turs have kicked out the net,
and we can tell you we've had a lot more people we can show that.
Have a lot of successful concerts this past weekend.
We have a well-attended concert on Friday night with the Texas Playboys,
and they've got over 600 folks there.
That night, we had at the time the holiday market that was going on.
in the bottom, which wasn't our members in our building, which continued through Saturday, but
lots of visitors coming into the home because these events are folks to town, and we thought
of a great idea when they went to pair those up. Sunday, we had a group from out of, I'm not sure
of everyone who was there, came from, look at the little girls, pageant that was held in just
little girls either. But our girls pageant from babies up through teenagers, and we was a really
great event. And after that was over, we had a wonderful concert that six-foot buck, we had a
group come in from the Marvel's Bill area with the, the Spring Court and the concert at evening.
So, we just say pretty busy around there, and we love it. We love what it brings to people, we've never
heard. Here, we never are surprised about every person who comes in, no matter whether coming from,
they are very appreciative of the building and of the job, and it's such a community effort that we put
out there. People leave with an appreciation for what our community is invested in in that building. We
left them know how the renovation was done by the community, and it was not a sponsorship from a corporation,
or anything that it was just that the community folks have invested in that and want to make it happen,
and they will leave, they see what a great community that we have right here in Miami. So,
we used to enjoy it for people's engines, and this is the best kept secret in Oklahoma. We say,
that's not fun. We're ordered, we don't want it to be a secret. So, you help us spread the word because we want
everyone to feel come out and enjoy the comment with us. When you said, we just said they're about being
the biggest kept secret. What's our marketing budget for, what's going on? Our marketing budget for the
Coleman. This year we give you just a second. That's the thing here. I believe that we,
are you looking at? I'm looking, I'm looking, it looks like 11,000, nine, and it's what it's.
What? All it wants? All year long. That's, I don't know if there's one that's the biggest kept secret in
Oklahoma. That's not a very big budget for marketing. The Goldman, wow. And that's the market all the
shows, and everything? The market the entity, the flagship of Route 66. So, you had the Texas boyboys.
What did you spend on marketing for that? That show was a rental. It wasn't our show that we presented.
So, we only added it with a lot of social media things. We included it with marketing that we do when we're talking.
about all the shows that will be at the comb of the S-decific show. We did not, I think,
amount of money from others themselves did that. So, they rented that for $1800? No, they
rented it or $750. So, $750? How much are they selling ticket for? They're tickets for $40.
For the premium seats, $30 for all the other. How many premium seats do they sell? I don't know
and $1.7. So, six hundred seats, just at $30. So, no premium seats. We made $750 and they made $18.
We'll step. So, any of the county about the rental model that they're thinking about that is really
can't make very much. If we do it that way, it does. I'm going to make some of the rest because
if it had fallen flat, any would still get this money for the common, but the people who put the show on
would get, you know, they would take the loss. On the other hand, we bring it in and we pay for it.
We're taking the risk if, you know, we don't make any money, but we also have an opportunity to make it.
Does that $750 cover your guys' labor if having people left? We, as we, as we, at this point, get $2
per ticket on every ticket that sells no matter what the show is in the common. And,
does that end of me also get the concession as money? That model, how long has it been that model for
rentals? As long as I know about it. So, when it's rental like that, so if you look at that,
we made $750, they might have taken in $18,000. It was a ride around that. They paid the band out of that,
so they paid $10 or $11,000 for that. They paid about $5,000 per standard with that, that are a
sound guy that they're probably in. I believe that they didn't make as much as they said initially,
so I made that a little less. And they have television advertising and radio advertising. I will be very
surprised if they made the dime. Okay, so let's talk about six. I know we talked about that. Yes.
So, six rents at $1800, and would you say they brought in? Well, they probably walked away the
night with near $50,000. We have changed the model. Yeah, it doesn't help us a great amount
that it helps us somewhat because now after 300 tickets are sold, we get a percentage at their ticket.
That's a big percentage. Bye. So, let's still come way with a lot of money. Let me get $1800.
So, I'd say I don't want to like that. We need a band in that model. Because we wouldn't have sold
over many tickets.
to make our 1800 and even what the type of spider was we'd have
sell 60 tickets at $30 to break our 1800 back.
So I don't think we're taking a big risk there.
Well, I think we had to pay the hand and all that.
Right.
Right, but I mean, in 1800, we don't have sell 60.
Well, that's not paying it.
You had to pay it to get here.
Right, but I mean, we only made 1800.
So we make that back off 60 tickets and then the rest.
You make with the band.
And we can market it a little different
and the right people around here.
I don't know where they marketed it to, but I think we probably
need to do one of them rate studies on this.
This right here is a great place for rates that I don't think
we're maximizing that on the rental.
Yeah.
So I live in an idea and you know, I think David Davis challenges a few weeks ago.
He said, I wish you guys would kind of beg us for some more money.
So you can bring in some paper performers.
So let me tell you how it worked with my name.
This was a little bit different model than the others.
And he told me about this was a commuter that I think the name.
And this was a time of code.
So a lot of things were shattered.
They weren't having any events.
And so that we're living for places that were willing to custom event,
even with code.
And so we were able to get why now we're here for $20,000.
Now normally, if any of you said it would be closer to $50,000
to bring our end, but we were able to get it for $20.
Now we didn't pay all of that the promoter paid $6,250,
and then we paid $14,750.
And then each of the risk, he paid for some of the advertising.
If you see, you know, like with radio and I guess I'll radio what we paid
for advertising, and then he paid a little bit of that as well.
And then of course we had to bring in a sound person, which was $5,000 or more equipment.
I know I didn't need your own equipment, too, because what we had was enough of what she needed.
So those were the main expenses.
And then the tickets sold worth $57,000, $222, taking out the ticket fee
and the credit card fees left a total profit out there.
And we took out their expenses and ours, but to total profit of $20,000, $440,000 and $13.
So that was split with the promoter and with us.
If you take that profit and you add our user fees,
because we also get $2,000 for a ticket, user fee.
And in concessions, and this isn't, this isn't pure profit, but this is just what was sold.
That night was $1,120, then our total profit on this was $13,187.
And now if she had charged her full amount, you know, we would have been in the hole.
So this is something we're going to have to look at.
We want to bring in big forgiveness, which I think I think we should.
But we're going to have to look at ways that we can do with that.
You know, Danny and I, and I will all admit it.
I don't think we go to a world we'll get risk of or a world that hasn't been to go out there and do something that we may end up losing our sharks on.
But they've told us to come big of a money.
And so I guess if we did, we could kind of say that we didn't want money.
But this is, you know, you have to keep in mind.
And of course, he doesn't always do one like this, but he wasn't going to pass the set.
But it's a kind of thing.
It's a high distance, how we'll work it.
You know, it turned out to be a really great deal.
But you would think of something like that, that we would have just had tons of money.
And it really wasn't a whole lot of profit.
Now, it did bring people in though.
And if they ate out and they, you know, put gas in their car, it's still a win.
Anyway, you look at it.
It's just, we got to be careful too, that we don't knock the bottom out of our budget.
And we also, we're able to do this with a lot of great volunteers.
We probably have 20 volunteers working that, you know, that are three or four employees.
And you want volunteers to come to get that.
This is a much better model.
And you know, I know there's people out there that fall in this price range.
Because since it's been working with a man on the festival, I kind of look at that stuff.
And always looking at who's available and what their prices are.
There's a bunch of them out there.
And I've actually talked to Lenny the same promoter that did.
I wanted to ask him about some of the stuff for the festival.
And he's got the connections to help us.
And he says he wants to.
So I say we use it.
And if he's going to help us, I mean, he's going to make money.
We're going to make money.
It's a win win.
But I love this model a lot better than the 18.
He's got money.
Like this model.
The other model for the event last night.
Do you know what I mean?
Take it.
So.
So we really came in great.
Well, but that's where that's where you come in.
You're a man or this guy.
You got to know which one to use, which model.
That's where the thing doesn't take away the one.
That's where the thing happens to you.
You got that model and you're going to use it.
I don't know.
So I'm freeing for that.
To kind of start out.
Get a sun, be in this price range and use them this model and just give it a try.
And see what we can.
From that.
Okay.
So.
So I wrote down some stuff Amanda said, and you said, over the next six months,
now you want to present what we travel in those people spend $106 per person per day.
So over the next six months, what can you put in there?
What can you use this model and put in there so we can try to capitalize on what she just said
about the amount of what percent of your material.
You use a different model for the glory market that's coming up.
Got a guy like Lenny, who would do it for just a small commission.
So we are, we're set to make more of the profit, keep more of the profit for our
software than to give them the money that we'll see on that one.
I think we should always go that long for it.
I like it.
So if you had the budget and the empowerment and the permission to fail, are there more
glory morgons out there?
Because safe in a market that's as hot as this one, maybe isn't necessarily the best approach.
Just in, I'm a risk-taker, I'm a self-employed guy, and I don't care if I say it, because I'm
going to learn something and try and get better.
And I know we will too, and it's bothered me, I've been here for bits and pieces of three
budget cycles now, and it's bothered me the whole time, and it didn't have anything to do,
very much with anybody in this room tonight.
And I respect you a ton, Martian, I respect you a ton, Danny, and I have no idea why a team
that goes and promotes an entity like this isn't responsible for an entity like this.
And that was made by a previous regime, that decision, and it bothers me a lot.
Because it's misaligned on its face, and if I'm misinformed, I trust that somebody
will demonstrate there in a while, but momentum matters, and this entity, the Coleman, is fabulous.
And my question is how do we, in this flourishing time, how do we get the investment model
right in that machine, the Coleman, whether it's what we were talking about Mr. Stole earlier,
it's it lights and sound, do those need upgraded to where we can get this hybrid model going a
little bit better, more often, to where we minimize risk, but still give ourselves some upside.
I don't know, but I think we've got to find out, and that's an investment issue, and an alignment
issue for me.
And I think for many of the folks that I said up here with, because it's like the sound, I mean,
if we every time we rent the sounds at $5,000, how long does that take before?
or we could have bought a set, have it,
and we say for itself $5,000 every time.
So, or sought a grant to get it upgraded.
I would assume there's plenty of money out there
for arts and humanities that possibly could apply
to our government for an upgrade.
If we get that investment model right,
then I'll get off my soapbox.
We can bet that thing will, that thing being the common,
be the light that we want it to be on the hill all the time,
not just part of it.
And you hear so much about the common,
because you can travel, you can go out of town,
people will ask where you from,
my aunt will say, oh, the common theater.
I mean, it's there.
We just got to promote it more,
and we've got to do something better to get you
where you need to be.
That way, Wayne Lee Martin was a comedian
that came to the common, he loved it.
He said the acoustics there were unbelievable.
Probably the best he'd ever had.
So, he wanted to come back and do his live show from there.
And I think you said, I don't know if I set up for that.
We should be.
We should be set up for that.
Because if someone's gonna be alive a bit from there,
we need to be saying, let's get this done.
Let's do this.
So, we need to give you the tools.
So, when somebody says that,
you say, well, let's get it signed up.
Let's go.
Let's get it booked.
Because if somebody's been alive from our place,
everybody's gonna see it.
And we need it out there.
You know, Tom from Square did their master piece of video
from there.
So, every time somebody sees their master piece of video,
there's a problem with the error.
So, you know, we need to highlight as much as possible.
And we got to invest and make the tools,
give it the tools to be the best that you can be.
And I wanted to be a destination to where,
when my note of Lee's, and she goes and tells them,
you gotta go play this place.
And the next person comes and they love it.
And then they go tell their celebrities or artists,
or whatever, you gotta go play this.
But I wanted to all to want to play here.
I want this to be a bucket list, check it off.
I want to play this part.
Help us to help you.
You might be, you know, I mean, it was,
I didn't spot the platform.
Absolutely.
I think both, I think, you know,
flushing out the different models,
also setting down like March and I talked about this morning,
and you, that we sat down with Jill and Amanda,
and let's just kind of think through the planning
for the next, you know, end of this fiscal year
through the next fiscal year, and talk about
what are our options if we want to increase these type
of events, what would that look like,
and how would we do it?
And that way, we can kind of bring them some options
and say, here's some models we think would work best for us.
Here's some types of events that we want to try to do.
And to your point, let's make sure we don't shoot ourselves
in the foot by getting rid of something we want.
Let's make sure they understand,
here's the total arsenal of options we want
to be able to offer.
And then make sure roll a line and go execute.
When did you say that out of that night to get that hit back?
Didn't, I still think you were trying to relay you long enough to think.
I said, let's say by the first of the year, let's say by the first of the year.
No way we can get on, you got one book to January, 2020, too.
Yeah.
And I think it's going to be a good one.
So if you get some backers by then, we can start having the ground run and get the rest of
2020, too.
But it gets some stuff in there.
Well, I've said to any couple of today, actually, Lenny, yeah, he's got Lenny's content.
They talk all the time.
Are you talking about the William Lee Martin?
Well, he knows how to get all that in as well.
He knows how to get all them.
And with that, the theater improvements that seem reasonable, practical and needed to get
us where we want to be.
And the quote to associate with that, yes, sir, because right now, what is the common, what
was it operating now?
But what do we make on the common?
We don't.
Currently the city expends $95,000 in a transfer to MRDA, MDRA, for the maintenance and operation
of the cold.
And if we do this right, we won't make that transfer anymore.
It can be self-sustained if we do this right.
It can be the quality of life, item that we want it to be, and break even, it's a victory.
And Ms. Jeele's back, your chicken and said, hmmm, so we're saying this, we're willing
to invest to get it there.
But we just like the ones that we want to sound like I'll do feet.
We think, I think you can be done.
You have Mr. Colvin built it to be a showboys.
Let's make a showboys.
Relations that hold up, it comes to upgrades and try to keep the architecture of the
building there.
And there is some work that needs to be done in fire states.
Facilities, bathrooms now, when you talk about expanding this to massive amount of people.
It's going to take some funding for some grants to get it to work in a whole new consistent.
With a historical part of it, I believe there is a lot of grants out there to be had on
it.
So I mean, I don't see a problem with maybe getting grants.
But we're not so much new grants.
It's one thing that allows facility to see a whole lot of changes about approval to the actual argument.
and we fought that on the fires,
came some back to the village for years,
and made new deaths for the name to be read down.
So that's just something to consider
when we talk about budgeting and funding,
there are some interior upgrades
other than lighting and sound
that needs to be addressed to that bill.
All right, well you have Robert quite on Dylan,
and he's got to the first of the year,
so so do you.
Yes or no?
The quantity is not the issue.
Right.
And growing the number of people's not the issue.
It's given the people the tools they need
while they're there in our facility.
We're at 11, 1200 max count in the back of the building.
Yeah.
That's fine.
Yeah, right.
Inside, I think the service I'll handle that about.
Right.
So that's five hundred and twenty.
Yeah, it's a basic thing, why don't you?
I think that's a lot on the concert.
My wife maybe go.
And I didn't want to go.
Didn't think of them good time.
And I think what's she from when they come to the concert?
It's fun.
I don't get time.
And I saw a lot of other people
coming at a great time as well.
But those sisters drove in from close to that of black and they were
here spending their money.
I promise you, I spend a hundred and six bucks a week.
So we need to capture everyone.
I think the wind and Lee Martin, we had a couple that said next to me
my wife from Claremore, we talked to them, they love coming to the
Column.
One of the things they told me was, you need to have more events.
We love coming here, have more stuff.
So when people from outside of the community, they're spending $1 to tell
you that, you got to listen, you have to give them more to come and see anything else?
Thank you, guys.
Yeah, thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you for your effort.
So I hope you know we're behind you.
Okay.
Oh, a hundred percent.
A hundred percent.
We're chef and hard.
Right.
The middle of your mind.
All right.
16.
Next night of mayor.
Mayor's nomination to appoint Ron Shirley to the city's only and planning
commission.
No move.
Second.
So cool.
Hi.
E-step.
Sunberg.
David.
17.
The other new business in the bank is the residents of the post of this agenda.
18.
Staff reports.
19.
Mayor and Council of the Community in the House.
I'd like to talk about something.
So I want to kind of go back to something Amanda said earlier about outdoor events and
having outdoor space.
During this seven after words, I met with.
Not just Matt Penel, but also his aide and then also one of our kind of commissioners
when we talked about a project to.
to start a Rails-to-trails program, which I think is already begun, and I think that they've already gotten some traction with that.
I just wanted to bring it up here as a means to get an in front of you guys to be thinking about, and how can we jump on this train?
How can we be a part of this? Because this provides another avenue to draw people to our area.
I mean, look what's happening in North West Arkansas. There's tons of trails, and not just walking trails, but biking trails.
It's amazing what they've got going on there, and if we can get on that, and have another, yet another thing to draw people into our area, I think it'd be in our best interest to push every button we can to make that happen.
And I want to say that I appreciate the script of man here, and both this weekend, there was a community event that a man to put on.
She got a great job, and then they had the board on, and she really took off.
And man, they kind of told us there was already a spot paid, so we got a team, and it was really fun though.
We were out seeing the community, the community was, I think, kind of surprised, that we were there, and being visible, and they can come and speak to us.
But I appreciate these guys giving up their part of their Saturday to come and do that.
And, and with one, we got first place.
But I didn't appreciate these guys, because I didn't have to go with our Saturdays or family.
We spent a lot of time going to our area.
Bends didn't show up, but no, it was fun.
I appreciate these guys, because we're always going to do that and be a face for the city and for the council, so I just want to appreciate them.
I still want to know who the all the judges was.
I was at 77, and then went to the chili bag off just on site that day, which was, I think, probably the largest one that they've ever had before, and the people coming through to take us for a box.
177 people came in eight chili?
Wow, I couldn't, I wouldn't have guessed that, because you were over talking to people.
What can the room be?
Sorry.
We think we had talks about eight hundred and about ten through the holiday market.
I mean, you think that's close to about a thousand people on the weekend.
For a lot of work, there were so many people that had come in and on how cool it was to see all the cities up there doing that.
It was great.
When I know you guys all care, but it was just great CR because it wasn't the community thing.
It was me.
It was fun and our chili was good
I can't I can't do that he'd love to
Bless you have any leftover we did bow I did all we said bow back
I didn't get them you left
So these Brian wasn't here so he didn't get any Kevin left there was a meeting in so
I have one more and then I'll promise to shut up for today
The we live in a society that is hyper critical and
That society is readily equipped with Facebook pages that facilitate that a lot of times taking shots at us a lot of times taking shots
That's you guys and that's not fair
I want to say thank you to Josh Fleming because he takes the time to come and at least visit about the issues
Get the details and then how we we have seen him correct folks that were making missed statements because he's taken the time to come and educating himself
People that invest
said time
We're the of being listened to those screaming at the wind are not and I hope this is being recorded and streamed somewhere if they don't want to be part of the solution
They should never be heard
But this guy is investing the time to be part of the solution and I respect that and appreciate it and I wanted to say thanks
Thank you
Good number 19
Now this is going to be our groups there to start up with something that's near and dear to Josh's heart
That is I
Talking to Justin and Kevin today and I need to do an ounce the ninth that we're going to start removing the disc golf baskets from yes Josh
Josh
Uses those out there every view park they've been there for a long time
But they're at the end of their life their the sedimentation is slowly lowering them to the point that
We're probably not regulation and yours are about that off the ground. Are we allowed to go put one on this right?
That's going to say
They probably have to be auctioned off as Ben would say
But we do have a course out there. It's got a court in ortho
but anyways, Josh, I hated to do that, but we do have to announce and want it to
count to the notes as to know that we're going to start removing those baskets.
Starting when guys, pretty quick.
Oh, wow.
You're going to go to my Josh.
Yeah.
Anyway, so I'm sorry, Josh.
The other thing I wanted to mention to was just to make Council citizens aware that we
continue to have vacancies in our Bateman crew.
We have not had an abatement crew since the late August.
We have opened these positions, I think at least three times now.
We have reason to hire a code officer and still have one vacancy there.
Our new code officer is beginning to go out and do inspections again in according to state
statute.
If a property is not brought up into compliance after 10 days, the letter is sent in the city
can debate the property as you all know.
But we also have the ability, in this case, when we don't have a crew that we can send those that
have not mitigated the problem after 10 days, we can take them to the municipal board.
And that's, unfortunately, the position we're in in order to get someone to respond and take care
of the grass, we'll care the weeds, take care of whatever issue has been identified.
Since we don't have a crew, we are just going to have to start sending those to municipal
court.
We are absolutely sensitive to the fact that we don't want to overload our municipal court.
So we will continue to monitor that and make sure that's not the case.
And of course, our goal is the event that we're able to hire an abatement crew, we'll go back to
be able to take care of what we can and just send people to build the hours of work and
not send them to court.
But this is the only thing we have left our arsenal and I think we've made great strides in
to clean up efforts that we've made and what the team has done.
We've just seen a lot of activity in that aspect, but what did you all to be aware and hope that
we have an abatement crew soon?
I've actually had a guy that had called me on that and I believe he was going to come and apply.
Well, I don't know if he has yet, but I've told him to come up and apply.
You know, I don't think it will take long.
You start putting me to municipal court and they're going to figure out how to put him up
on the yard or better victims to clean up my yard.
Much to be able to see the judge here and also off.
If it's a matter of moment or long, it's much cheaper to find someone that can do it, find a crew that
can do it, find the neighbor kid down the street that can do it, it's a lot cheaper than
paying us to do it and certainly cheaper than paying, coming to paying a fine.
So I hope that's the way it works out because we don't want to, we don't want to attempt
to take you to the court.
We don't want to have this.
We don't want to go to the amate. We'd rather than find somebody to take care of.
City court staffs on salary, right?
That's a good choice, yeah.
Sure.
A lot of them. Maybe it might be a bad one. Maybe it's a judge who gets 16 of you.
So that was a fine.
They'll come back and see.
Yes.
I mean ultimately that's what we'd like to see is changed baby.
And that's all I've got.
That's what it is.
The German.
So move.
Second.
Thank you.